Archdiocese of St. Paul and Minneapolis Collection
University of Notre Dame Archives
Archdiocese of St. Paul and Minneapolis Collection
1860-1899
ASM
1 linear inch.
University of Notre Dame Archives Notre Dame, Indiana 46556
Scope and Content
Occasional letters from Bishop Grace and Archbishop Ireland; sermons preached by Ireland for the Golden Jubilee of the University of Notre Dame and Father Sorin's ordination, and for the peace jubilee of 1898; also an English translation of Ireland's Memorial to the Holy See (1892) concerning the Faribault School Plan, and Archbishop Keane's sermon on Ireland's receiving the pallium as Archbishop; a transcription of Ireland's history of his own service as a chaplain during the Civil War; a transcription of a short history of the early years of St. Paul.
Background
The diocese was created in 1850, with Joseph Cretin as its first bishop. He was suceeded in 1859 by Thomas L. Grace, O.P., who was then succeeded in 1884 by John Ireland. The diocese was raised to a metropolitan see in 1888, with John Ireland as archbishop. The Province of St. Paul, with its metropolitan and nine suffragan sees, comprises the area of Minnesota, North Dakota, and South Dakota.
Catholic Church. Archdiocese of St. Paul and Minneapolis (Mn.); Catholic Church -- Minnesota; Grace, Thomas Langdon, Bishop, 1814-1897; Ireland, John, 1838-1918
Related Material
John Ireland Papers
Marvin Richard O'Connell Papers
Helen Angela Hurley Papers
- Archdiocese of St. Paul and Minneapolis: Manuscripts, 1860-1899; CASM
  - Sermons, Oration, Memorial, CASM /1
    - Sermon at the conferring of the Pallium on Archbishop Ireland by Rt. Rev. Bishop Keane, CASM /1.01
    - Sermon by Abp. Ireland for Fr. Sorin's Golden Jubilee (copy sent to J.F. Edwards), CASM /1.02
    - English translation of Abp. Ireland's Memorial to the Holy See, 1892; CASM /1.03; His explanation and defense of the Faribault School Plan.
    - Sermon by Abp. Ireland for Golden Jubilee of Notre Dame, CASM /1.04
    - Abp. Ireland's Oration at the Peace Jubilee, Chicago, October, 1898; CASM /1.05
  - Early History of St. Paul, 1868/1015; CASM /2; Photostat of handwritten "Early History of St. Paul" by John A. Farmsworth, 15 October 1868, with a spirit-duplicator typewritten transcription.
  - Letters and Ephemera, CASM /3; Several miscellaneous letters and transcriptions of letters, a clipping, a photocopy of a photo of Abp. Ireland, and a dinner menu.
    - Bp. Thomas L. Grace to Fr. George Keller, 1860/0417; CASM /3.01
    - Fr. George Keller, Covington, Louisiana, to Bp. Thomas L. Grace, St. Paul, 1860/0425; CASM /3.02
    - Col. Leith to Bp. Thomas L. Grace, 1868/0308; CASM /3.03
    - John Ireland to Editor of Detroit Free Press, 1880/1201; CASM /3.04
    - Rev. Ireland to Rev. T. Cooney, 1884/1015; CASM /3.05
    - John Ireland to Miss Angela Ewing, 1885/0326; CASM /3.06
    - John Ireland to Father Cooney, 1892/0124; CASM /3.07
    - John Ireland describes his own early career as chaplain in the Civil War, CASM /3.08
    - Photocopy of small photo of John Ireland, CASM /3.09
    - Dinner Menu on occasion of conferring the Sacred Pallium on Rev. John Ireland, 1888/0927; CASM /3.10
    - "A Trio of New Bishops; Archbishop Ireland Acts as Consecrator" - Chicago Tribune, 1889/1228; CASM /3.11